hi welcome back to lamrim
and uh we're at diamond mountain and
thanks to all the crews especially um
[Music]
and this is a really exciting home room
i like it because
we finally reached bodhichitta after 10
years
of working on this uh lamrim book
uh we've reached finally go to china we
have done
36 retreats already
in 10 years and this is number 37
and i i just feel like
we're sitting in a bath in a warm cup
you know finally after struggling
through impermanence and
the sufferings of all the realms and
things like that then finally we get
to talk about
beautiful things like bodhichitta and
and you know
being a bully suffer and so let's jump
into it this is a
typical uh device used by the
buddhist teachers where they
sell you an idea okay it's like i don't
know
in america we say like selling your car
you know
i if you spot a car recently i mean you
go to the place
and the guys are they're really good at
it
you know by the time you leave the
you you feel like it's almost patriotic
to buy this car
you know and that you're getting but
this guy's
the car seller is a bodhisattva and he
just wants you to have this car
at a good price and and i don't know
it's very hard to to not listen to them
they're very convincing and it's what
they do
and they and they judge you immediately
they understand you know
how to talk to your immune and it's
amazing so anyway
it's a tradition in buddhism that you
sell
a great idea and you talk about how cool
is it
so i i think we're going to enjoy this
particular
alarming retreat because the whole thing
is a sales job about
why getting bored each other is so cool
why it's so cool to have bodhichitta so
for me it's fun it's going to be
fun a fun retreat and then uh today
i think we have a special class after
this class
we'll have a special discussion between
myself and dr
wu about the medicine buddha practice
and where does it fit into the lumberjam
and what we're doing now
so we'll do an hour of that and then
we'll come back to the
to the benefits of bodhichitta i think
it's important to
i'm i'm lucky because i was not a
buddhist
when i first heard these teachings so i
i was just
i had just got to yeah i was just in my
first classes
there was a a gashai teaching
catching on darger and he had a
translator
sharpa rinpoche tenzin chimney who's in
the badger guinea
and and
i didn't know anything and
and there was about 20 hippies from
different countries
and we didn't know anything and
so there were lots of misunderstandings
in the beginning the the translator
uh was very young and the geshe was from
a very strange
eastern dialect part of to that where
they spoke a strange thailand
so the whole thing was uh a study in
misunderstanding
you know we would learn words and then
we'd all
talk about it uh in a mistaken way for a
couple weeks and then finally somebody
would say no no i figured out it's not
that you know
so bodhichitta is one of those words
that
it took about i don't know it actually
took a few months for us to figure out
what it wasn't and so bodhi means buddha
right
and then chitta means mind so
everybody was calling an enlightened
mind or buddha mind
and then uh it was confusing because
you're supposed to get it
you're supposed to study it in order to
become a buddha
but if you got it how come you're not a
buddha if you already have a buddha mind
you know and it was very confusing and i
mean the whole
transmission of buddhism to these
hippies
in the himalayas you know who made it to
the himalayas
some people walked you know took buses
across turkey and iran
and we didn't know what was going on and
it took so long to figure out
that bodhichitta doesn't mean buddha
mind
uh it means the wish to become a buddha
okay so here chitta means wish
the aspiration to become a buddha
and then you're like well that's why i
came here to the himalayas and it was
hard you know that's why i have diarrhea
this week the whole week
because you know
i have a desire to become a buddhist so
why do i have to study that you know
that's why i'm here
and then they say no no no there's the
real one and there's the
almost real one sugar cane
tastes like sugar but it's not real
sugar sugar can't skin about each other
so so then we were like wait a minute
bodhichitta is not buddha mind right and
buddha mind means
i want to be a buddha mind right and
there's a real i want to be a buddhist
mind and there's a not real i want to be
a good of mine
right and then you we just got all
confused
and then the the translator didn't speak
much english actually
it was i don't know but we learned
better somehow because
nobody understood anything and we had to
figure things out
so anyway i guess there's a point right
where you have the real desire to become
a buddha okay
then there's a question of uh
does it have to be a direct cosmic
experience
do you have to have some thing happen
maybe while your channels are open maybe
while you're promised
running free uh maybe after you see
emptiness directly you know do you get
body cheated before that or do you get
bodytalk after that
and is there like a super body tuner
where you
where you can actually see all the
beings in the world or something in the
universe
so uh all these questions came up
and we're gonna try to straighten those
out okay so i guess the first thing to
say
is that bodhichitta is not it's not that
you're already enlightened right
uh bodhichitta is what makes you
there are gonna be 10
different selling points for bodhichitta
and as we go through the different
advertisements for bodhichitta
then you'll start to understand what it
is better
and the first way to approach it
traditionally is to find out how cool is
it
to get both each other okay so i i think
it's gonna be a really fun
uh retreat because it's just
you know 15 classes of
how cool is it to get bloody china you
know and how cool is it to get that
and then by learning how cool is it
uh we're gonna learn about how to do it
how to get it
okay and it's not easy you know they
talk about it
in this retreat about a sangha
arya who worked for 12 years
in a cave to get bodhichitta and and
they say it's not easy
it's not like you're going to hear one
retreat and then suddenly you're going
to get put each other it's going to take
a lot of work
so it's it's something that's like i
think it's like learning piano or
something it takes a lot of commitment
and it's going to take time and it's
difficult
it's not that you can just sit down and
start doing it you know
it takes a lot of work you have to work
at it and it's worth it
you know there's 10 cool things are
going to happen to you
if you get it so the first cool thing we
covered in the last retreat
number 36 and that was uh
take take changes you go say take chin
juko and by the way i'll go through the
original language first of all because
it's such a huge blessing
the teacher who taught this text
papankarimpuche
is probably in my opinion the greatest
teacher
of the last century uh an
unbelievable teacher able to teach to
normal people
he was a geshe from my
college geron content
in serene monastery which is the best
tibetan monastery
and uh just kidding not
and uh he was also ling say guessing
which is my
level of gishi he was a
you know he wasn't the highest highest
highest
level but he was a he was a ling
signation maybe called second level
geshe
and then he was known
for his ability to talk to normal people
so he was very popular among the normal
people of tibet the farmers and the
herders and the
people like business people and
military people he was very famous for
being able to talk to normal people so
anyway
and the book he wrote was
the teaching he gave for 24 days
was edited by chija rinpoche who was my
teacher's teacher
and he's
such a great writer and such a great
thinker
that and i believe he spent about 10
years
writing the transcript fixing the
transcript
and i i believe that this book is the
greatest example of tibetan
literature there is this is the greatest
book ever written in tibetan language i
think so
uh and the language is the greatest that
was ever written in tibetan and
and after that uh because of the
political problems in tibet
the the level of the language dropped
and so i think it will always stand as
the greatest example
of tibetan writing there ever was so i'm
i'm gonna teach you directly from the
book and it's not just for you it's for
future generations also who
who maybe want to learn it otherwise
it'll be gone
i think this tradition will be gone and
my teacher taught it for 30 years
he taught it three times through and so
i because i was his
uh assistant what do you call that
attendant
slave uh i got to hear all three
i was the only person who heard all
three so uh
anyway it was an honor to be able to do
it
so the first advertisement we already
covered in the last class take change
means mahayana the greater vehicle
greater capacity okay people have
greater capacity we were just talking
about moms
people who are moms and they they have
more
capacity than i've never been a mom in
this life
so but i can observe that
moms have greater capacity than other
people so
they're just able to do more
to help more people to they're able to
give up themselves
for other people my students there's a
virus there's a second virus going on
in sedona it's a baby virus everyone's
having babies
and i mean from one way it's very
irritating for me
because you know like a translator gets
sidetracked for 10 years and you know i
have to put up with bad translations
during while the kids growing
but on the other hand
they gain something especially the boys
who have babies they have they learn
self selflessness they learn how to not
be selfish
they learn to give themselves up for
somebody else so and then in the end i
think it makes them
a great translator so i put up with the
ten years it's okay
uh but if you've had a child and you've
made those sacrifices then you're a
different kind of person
so that's like mahayana jupgo means
once you get bodhichitta once you get
the wish
to become a buddha for all living beings
then
juko means you enter the you enter
mahayana you are in a different class of
people
okay and i
i don't know the way i grew up at
princeton i studied buddhism
and uh you know there's mahayana
historical
schools and then there's hinayana
historical schools
theravada schools and it's a different
school
and i don't know in princeton it was
quite
dry the difference between the schools
was very dry
and boring you know i still remember how
boring it was
and so if you tell me oh if you get this
buddy cheddar you become mahayana i'm
like well
that's not that's not so exciting it's
just a different
dry school you know you go from one dry
school to the other dry school wow
[Music]
and it it's not like that experientially
okay mahayana here doesn't mean
a different school of buddhism or a
different historical school of buddhism
okay what it means is
you join a very very select group
of people you you join a very unusual
group of people
we kind of do it in dci we in dci we
have a thing called diamond club
and when we used to tour around the
world before the virus
there would be maybe five or six maybe
10 people
in each country uh who were invited to
join the diamond club and
and they would be extraordinary people
and and then those people
[Music]
in different countries it was kind of
cool because
it's basically you took the 10
most amazing people from from 20
different countries
and then you kind of threw them together
and it was a special
experience what i'm trying to say is you
take a country of 100 million people
like mexico
uh or a billion point 1.4 billion people
like
china or 1.39 billion
india which will pass china in this
decade i think
uh in population
so and you take uh three or four special
people from those people
then that's going to be a very unusual
group of people
now if you
take from each planet uh maybe 10 people
from each planet then
then think of that as mahayana think of
that as mahayana
it's a club it's a it's a
how do you say that not executive but
it's it's very
exclusive club of of unusual
people who have had a certain experience
and that experience is the direct
experience of bodhichitta
you know they have and and that's i
don't know
what all i want to say for the next 15
classes is one thing uh if you have that
experience
of real bodhichitta then you have the
experience of
jumping from planet to planet billions
of planets
billions of inhabited planets
you have this strange experience of
jumping from planet to planet
and me meeting each living creature
directly so
all the fish all the birds all the
humans
directly you meet them one by one
directly and you
establish a bond with them you establish
a commitment with them
so think of it as jumping and committing
or something like that okay
jumping from planet to planet and making
a personal connection with
with the i think there's a hundred
billion animals on this planet for
example
so you know 80 billion something like
that so you
you meet them directly you make contact
with them
each one individually and then
and then you become slightly changed by
that experience
then that's mahayana okay that's mahana
it's not some uh
school of buddhism okay that's not it
mahayana means
you have made a personal connection with
countless billions of people
uh beings and and you've made a
commitment to them
a loving commitment similar to what a
parent makes with their child
uh deeper to help them okay
and and that's that puts you in a
special club
and and that's what the first that's the
first selling point of the bodhichitta
new car
you know you will join uh an exclusive
and extremely exclusive club it doesn't
mean that you
it doesn't mean to exclude other people
it's not exclusive in that sense it's
just that
if you just learned these instructions
and if you just try to do them
then something will happen to you
as a as a being and you become a
different kind of being you become a
mahayana being so it's like
a different evolution of a person
into something higher close to god a
being who is close to god
something like that like like
it's a very very beautiful thing and and
it's very
small group of people who are able to do
it so even to hear
the instructions even to sit through
this class
for the next what 10 days to hear it
is extremely unusual karma you know you
you must be close to it if you get to
hear about it
because you don't get to hear about this
well you know
they didn't teach this at princeton or
anything
you know you don't learn this anywhere
else
some you must be an unusual person and
you must be very close to the door
of the clubhouse to join that
group of people to enter the clubhouse
of the mahayana you must be very close
if you are listening to these
instructions so so
open your mind open your heart listen
uh it sounds impossible you know it
sounds like oh geshla
that's that's nice you know i'm not that
kind of person i
i'm not special like that i'm not one
person out of a millionaire
or 10 million i'm just kind me you know
i'm not that special but he's going to
uh pabunkramache is going to show why
you are
and if you are listening to this talk
right now
it already proves that you are qualified
to be a planet jumper okay
you are very close by definition you are
very close if you are listening to this
talk right now
so just relax learn the
instructions and then try and it's so
fun
it's so cool to to jump over a few
billion planets and
meet everybody and make this
bond with them and that's that
that's what it means to join the
mahayana so that's the first
selling point for bodhi today and we
finished it already we finished it in
the last
in the last retreat so let's go to the
second oh by the way you guys have an
image for me for the first one right
which is i like to call it joining the
tennis team
and tim i have a setting
i'm seeing the settings over the poor
tennis player's face
this the setting screen uh
but yeah there you go yeah so i don't
know
this means a lot to me because i spent
many years in
school trying to get on the tennis team
and
finally i got on it it's only 10 people
are allowed
i was numbered 10 and a half or
something
but i got in and so it's a
it's sort of an exclusive group of
people
and and that's the kind of feeling i
want you to feel you know
like if you work hard
you can make that team and it's hard
and it takes hard work it does take a
lot of hard work okay
all right let's go on to the second
benefit
and we're gonna start let's let's show
the picture first you guys we have a
image this is uh
getting your college degree and
you know a funny thing when i graduated
from princeton i didn't attend the
graduation because i had to work i was
on scholarship
and that was the last week of work
and then i paid off my loans the day i
left in cash
and uh i worked three jobs for four
years
and anyway uh
i didn't get to go to the graduation i
was actually setting up the tables for
the drinking party afterwards
but uh so uh i didn't get to go to that
graduation
but i did uh you know not too long ago
my friends in
mexico invited me to the congress
in unam yeah
this that it's the oldest college in in
in
south and north america and it has 30
000 students i think
in total so they gave me a phd and i
felt so
i felt so honored you know to get a phd
in the congress and but then they
started calling me dr roach and it
sounded really weird
like some kind of insect doctor and
i didn't really use the doctor after
that
but to get a phd after my name
even though i already have a geshe that
was kind of i don't know it felt cool
you know i felt it felt like a big honor
to me
and and that to get up there and you
wear a special suit
and uh all these
fat cats what do you call
gato por porto
por gordo gato gordos
they were all giving me you know stuff
and we became friends actually and
that's where a green stretch pin came
from
from that this
attempt to help all the kids in mexico
but uh what i want to say is
it's nice to get a title you know it's
nice that someone
says that you're a geshe or you're a phd
and that's the second benefit of getting
bodhichitta what's the title you get
buddies and you know
i don't know about you but this word
bodhisattva is so beautiful
you know i i don't know about you but uh
there's a song in
in in the hippie days called bodhisattva
and just the word bodhisattva sounded so
sweet
and we didn't know exactly what it meant
but
it was such a beautiful word and it was
such a beautiful sound
that yeah i'd like to be called the
bodhisattva that's the second benefit
okay people will call you bodhisattva
you get your buddhist degree
oh you get your bodhisattva title
added to your name and i know it it
sounds weird
that oh you should work hard to get
bodhichitta because then they'll call
you bodhisattva alex or bodhisattva
janus
and and it sounds kind of artificial
geshe-la it's more important to be a
bodhisattva than to get the title
but it's nice come on you know it's nice
when someone uh
looks at you and says oh look there's
somebody suffering you know
and it's the real thing you know we tend
to think that if someone's
a nice person they make you a coffee at
five o'clock in the morning
you say oh that person must be a bunny
supper
but but to be called a
a member of the club of people who have
jumped planets
to get you know i'm in the club of
people who have jumped planets
and billions of planners
and then to be recognized by anybody as
a bodhisattva
uh and to be called a bodhisattva is
it's it's a big deal it feels really
good
especially if it's true you know it
feels amazing
yeah i like it i i'm happy to be mr
buddhist of the
geisha doctor roach
let's not okay anyway uh
so let's go to the text you guys we're
gonna talk we're gonna go through the
text note
i'm forcing you gonna go through the
text
i've been doing it for 10 years i have
gotten 10 years of steady complaints
from people who don't want to go through
the text
they say it's too difficult and it's i
don't want to learn that
and just teach me the thing and i don't
care just shut up
and i'm going to teach you the text it
puts a huge scene in your mind
okay the people who wrote these texts
are bodhisattvas and this is what they
decided to write
and it's unbelievable it's just
unbelievable so to
the whole purpose of this retreat
is to put seeds in your mind you're you
very probably you won't be a bodhisattva
by the end of this regime
but there will be seeds planted in your
mind
that will open into being a bodhisattva
and and actually if you're foolish
enough to sit through these
talks you probably will get seeds that
are unstoppable okay so sooner or later
you're going to be a buddhist officer if
you sit through this retreat
okay how soon is up to you
but uh you will get the seeds
and a lot of the sins are transmitted
uh through the ancient wisdom through
the ancient books
and um and i i really do think it's
extremely important to
stick to a real lineage you know
and and one thing i can say without
pride or without uh
exaggeration is that this is a real
lineage
this lineage was carried on for two and
a half thousand years
100 generations purely
very very pure extraordinarily pure
and if you just hang in there
you will become a body supply and these
are the correct
instructions and they have a real
lineage
and we are honoring that lineage by
learning those
ancient languages you don't have to
learn tibetan or sanskrit
or chinese you don't have to but to hear
it
is a powerful powerful scene and
you will get that experience much much
faster
of jumping by the way there's no more
fun experience in the world except
seeing emptiness directly
then jumping around planets and getting
to know
everybody in the universe okay
there's nothing like it once you've had
that experience
it's it's very hard to have a bad day
you can have a sort of bad day but not a
real bad day
okay it's like so what what's
who cares about anything else if you've
met everybody in the universe
and made the commitment of a mother to a
child to them
then how are you going to have a real
bad day you know
so okay here we go
uh first we have a quotation chandra
senke gerna ke
get you guys ready with the tibetan here
we go
yay anybody up just above that means
here's the second benefit
of of getting bodhichitta which is you
get
the title of uh mr bolista for miss
bodhisattva
if it comes up in your heart
in a single finger snap in a single
fingers now
korwei tsun dampe a person
who is chained in the prison of samsara
a person who is chained into a mortal
body
which is gonna die and fall apart those
of us over a certain age we
when we get together we just talk about
our doctors it's really funny
you know hey i got this new man wow you
know
and uh so we are locked in this body we
are chained to this body if you're under
50 or 60 you don't know what i'm talking
about yet but you will
okay and it begins to feel like you're
chained to
uh a mortal body which is what you are
okay so
in a single instant even a person who is
chained to a mortal body
yum tat means those poor poor people who
are chained to a mortal body
day sheikh namki say third line deshay
nam kise
we call you a daughter or a son
of the buddha okay even you are chained
to a
mortal body that's falling apart okay if
your body's not falling apart yet
that's the worst thing is you don't even
know it because it is
okay if you breathe you're falling apart
okay
it just shows it becomes more obvious
after a while
okay but even those people who are
chained to
a falling apart body if they can just
get this body to experience
then all the buddhas say hey hey that's
my daughter that's
my son hey that's my son
that's my daughter so even as you are
chained to a
falling apart mortal body the buddhists
are so proud of you
they're like ah that's that's one of
mine
that's my kid you know so that's the
second
benefit they'll call you a bodhisattva
or
okay child of the buddhas
okay child of the victorious buddha
nice name really nice name
they will call you okay uh
so i would say the next
image you guys if you have it
uh of my father hugging his daughter
yeah this is how i like to imagine it
you know
like it's not just that you get a paper
that says europe official bodhisattva
now bodhisattva cat you know it's it's
written the buddhist gave you your
degree
and now you can add it to your titles
you know
it's not just that it's that you enter a
new family
you take on a new status okay can you
show the picture
yeah you got it uh
is there any way to drop the chat from
my screen
uh just so i can see yeah that's nice so
i like i like this guy
i like to imagine that this father is a
buddha
and that he's hugging jail sei
his daughter you know or his son his
buddy sappa the new bodhisattva so
it's cool that you get a new title
they call you a bodhisattva that's nice
but to me what's more important is you
become
gelse which means you become an official
daughter
or son of the family you join it's like
a mafia family
you join the family you're in the family
you know you now you're a gambino or
something i don't know
you know you're part of the you're part
of the family
and and think of how it feels
that the enlightened beings of the world
sitting on the beach with you
hug you because they're so happy you're
part of the family now
and that's to me that's the more
important thing than the
than the title bodhisattva yes you are a
bodhisattva but you're
more importantly you're a gina putra
you are a child of the of the you are
their special kid
and they hug you like that and to be
hugged by the buddhas and be called
their kid
that's such a beautiful experience right
to join that family to be
recognized as a member of the new family
like you married into the family of
buddhists
that's awesome it's an awesome feeling
okay
and by the way that quotation above was
from
master shanti devas a guide to the
bodhisattvas way of life
and in this section pablo karimpache is
going to lean
heavily on master shantiduma the opening
lines
of that extraordinary work talk about
the benefits of becoming a bodhisattva
and and so pabong
is a lot of the quotations are going to
be taken from shanti davis work
and if you can study shanti davis work
it's extremely important that's aci
courses
10 11 12. yeah and very very important
you have no excuse not to study them
by the way i've been getting a lot of
questions lately
people say well now you've loaded
medicine bananas
and you lotus and long ramonas and you
got all the mixed nuts and classes and
you know
it's too much question you know
i'm starting to feel overwhelmed and i
say i don't care
okay it's better to be overwhelmed than
to die
okay so i don't care you know you got to
eat as much as you can
as i can feed you and you just have to
do it
okay i'm sorry i i'm reminded
of a moment in my diamond business
when the the owner of the company called
me in and said
how long does it take you to buy 10 000
diamonds
the factory manager is complaining about
you i said well it takes about two weeks
and he said well i want it in 24 hours
no
and i'm like you can't buy 10 000
diamonds in 24 hours it's not possible
he said fedex delivers 25 million
packages every day
overnight you can buy 10 000 diamonds
in 24 hours just do it you know
and i'm like it's not possible he says
what's your title in this show me your
business card
at that time i was a manager he says
you're a manager right i said yeah he
says
manage goddamn manage get out of my
get out he threw me out get out of my
office you're a manager so manage okay
you're a buddy stop it so deal with it
okay
you're gonna get a lot of teachings you
know
you should be happy you shouldn't be
convention you know this yiddish diamond
company word don't complain that
somebody complained to me geshe-la i
live in a tent
all the courses you wrote take half the
tent up
i don't have room to sleep okay so sleep
outside
i don't care okay
deal with it okay you're a manager
manager okay
learn everything and later you'll thank
me that's what
all parents say right jim later you'll
thank me
all right here's a very famous line from
shanti damon
[Music]
very very famous this is part of the
bodhisattva vowel ceremony
in fact if you just say those lines
supposedly you can get bodhisattva
vowels
you know at least a commitment though uh
tearing sangerix uk today i have become
today i have joined the beautiful family
of the buddhas sangee says
i have become a child of the buddhas
okay
and that's again a very very famous
lines from shanti
i'd like to read you the whole line his
version which is not the version used
nowadays into that okay
uh here we go
teng do doctor debut me super liberator
it's not in the text okay
i'll just translate quickly um
[Music]
finally i did something useful with my
life
me super labor talk now you can say i
have truly
taken on a human birth why
tearing sanjirik's okay because today i
joined the buddhist
family sangee says says
drenyer i became a child of the buddha
today
because i took my buddhist house donnie
chinese now i have an extra
responsibility
right on timberland someday i have to
behave in a way that reflects
well on my family i can't embarrass my
family
okay i've just been accepted into a new
this is i'm now i'm buddha family
member buddha clan member
now i have a new opportunity i can
embarrass
my new parents if i act in a selfish way
you know if i don't sacrifice my desires
for others
then i will embarrass my family and
they'll wish that i hadn't married into
their family
i therefore i promise i will never know
my family nyopa means
if you make somebody a nice cappuccino
and you accidentally
pour some engine oil into it that's
called nyopa
okay what do you call that like
adulterate with some crap it's called
yoga
okay i will not adulterate the buddha
family with my
crap i will be a good kid
i'll make my family proud my new family
okay all right let's go back to the
tibetan you guys ready
uh galway says
the whole big question in your life
is did you get into the family or not
were you accepted into the family or not
[Music]
i don't care whether you can read other
people's minds
i don't care whether you can fly in the
sky
rig i don't care if you have
mastered if you have phds in every
subject in the world
i don't even care if you've seen
emptiness directly
i don't care if you have eliminated your
mental afflictions
[Music]
you simba if you don't have this
attitude
we don't call you but it's suffer you
don't you don't get to be
you can see emptiness and not be a
bodhisattva you can fly in the sky and
not be a bodhisattva you can heal people
and not be a bodhisattva okay min
and not be a child of the buddha take
change
and we can say you haven't joined the
family yet it's
it's have you jumped the worlds or not
that's the question okay
next next pair samdi gila panna
i like this one you guys got the image
of this animal
this handsome animal yeah
that's a jackass and not a brutal is
different
okay jack bruto is bro is stubborn but
useful
jackass is just painful okay
and why i showed it here keep it up okay
you guys 70 gillard
if you manage to get body cheddar in
your heart
you intention maybe i'm touching you
too you could be a dog you could be a
pig
[Music]
you could be yin tenshin may be limba
you could be
as stupid as a jackass
but still you're part of the family
okay chase it to chase it soon means
you have been accepted as a member of
the family
and i i love this paragraph
each paragraph of this text
is packed with meaning you could take
one paragraph and meditate on it for
a week you know it was very hard for me
to choose
which paragraphs are more important or
it's very very difficult
every single paragraph is stunning and
exquisite
you know so anyway
this means look we all
are human right we all have faults
if you spend your whole life which i
have
trying to be a good person and you fail
many times then you start to feel like
some kind of idiot
or or a donkey or a horse or something
feel like a spiritual idiot
you know like you try really really hard
and then still you have bad habits that
you can't get rid of you know
and and bad attitudes that you can't get
rid of
and and some llama spent their whole
life trying to fix you
and you still feel like an idiot
then there's hope right okay papon
crippy jay says there's hope
okay even you guys who tried
so hard for so many years
to improve yourself and it's just
you ha you feel like you haven't made
much progress
he said still you can be part of the
family
we love you kind of guys you know
we especially enjoy welcoming into our
family
people who have bad habits they can't
get rid of
but as long as you jump a few planets
you can be in the family
okay and you don't have to be perfect to
be in this family
okay you don't have to be
perfect to be a bodhisattva a
bodhisattva is studying
to be perfect but they are not perfect
already
the reason you become a bodhisattva
is to learn how to be perfect so we love
imperfect bodhisattvas because if you're
a perfect bodhisattva you're a buddha
and we don't take buddhas into the
family
they're already family okay we want
bodhisattvas and bodhisattvas are people
who are imperfect and and they have bad
habits
that they've been struggling against for
decades
many years and they have broken all
these vows
that their llama gave them and they have
not been able to do their practice and
netflix
took over their mind and
we love those guys well that's the kind
of people we want in the family
we want uh body stuff us who are
trying to be good and turning sang
eunuch's okay
today we welcome into the buddha family
imperfect people who want to be perfect
and and that's what we really want those
are the people we are really
looking for okay so we're gonna stop
there
uh today and we'll take a break
and you know go run and have a pee pee
and a coffee or something
and then we'll come back in about 10
minutes
and we'll have a nice conversation with
with dr wu
about the medicine buddha practice and
the mom room practice okay see all your
body stop us in
about 10 minutes okay